<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>By the King. A proclamation against excesse of lauish and licentious speech of matters of state</title>
            <title>Proclamations. 1621-07-26</title>
            <author>England and Wales. Sovereign (1603-1625 : James I)</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1621</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 4 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 1 1-bit group-IV TIFF page image.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A22256</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 8668</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S100937</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99836764</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99836764</idno>
            <idno type="VID">1050</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A22256)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 1050)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1601:25)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>By the King. A proclamation against excesse of lauish and licentious speech of matters of state</title>
                  <title>Proclamations. 1621-07-26</title>
                  <author>England and Wales. Sovereign (1603-1625 : James I)</author>
                  <author>James I, King of England, 1566-1625.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>1 sheet ([1] p.)   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>by Bonham Norton, and Iohn Bill, printers to the Kings most excellent Maiestie,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>M.DC.XXI. [1621]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"Recites Proclamation 24 Dec 1620 ... against bold discourse on matters of State which still goes on. All persons are to cease from such discourse, on pain,&amp;c. All subjects are to discover and bring to justice offenders." -- Steele.</note>
                  <note>Dated at end: Ashbie, the sixe and twentieth day of Iuly, in the nineteenth yeere of our reigne ... .</note>
                  <note>Steele notation: the and vnrespec-; Arms 11.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the originals in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery (Early English books) and the British Library (Misc. Brit. tracts).</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Freedom of speech --  Law and legislation --  Great Britain --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="royal_proclamation">
            <pb facs="tcp:1050:1"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 18 -->
            <head>
               <figure>
                  <q>HONI SOIT QVI MAL Y PENSE</q>
                  <figDesc>royal blazon or coat of arms</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </head>
            <head>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> By the King.</head>
            <head type="sub">
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> A Proclamation againſt exceſſe of lauiſh and licentious ſpeech of matters of State.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hereas Wee by our Proclamation, giuen at Whitehall the</hi> foure and twentieth day of December laſt, did publiſh and declare Our Royall pleaſure againſt the licentious paſſage of lauiſh, and bould diſcourſe, then growen too frequent; And did thereby fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warne, and ſtraitly commaund all Our louing ſubiects, from the higheſt to the loweſt, to take heed how they did intermedle by pen or ſpeech with cauſes of ſtate, and ſecrets of gouernement, either at home or abroad, but containe themſelues within that modeſt and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerent regard of matters aboue their reach, and calling, that to good and duetifull ſubiects apperteineth; As alſo not to giue attention, or any manner of applauſe, or entertainement to ſuch diſcourſe, without acquainting ſome of Our Priuie Counſell, or other principall officers therewithall, reſpectiue to the place where ſuch ſpeeches ſhould bee vſed, within the ſpace of foure and twentie howers, vnder paine of im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſonment, and Our High diſpleaſure; And yet Wee are giuen vnderſtand, that notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the ſtrictneſſe of Our commandement, the inordinate libertie of vnreuerent ſpeech, touching matters of high nature, vnfit for vulgar diſcourſe, doth dayly more and more increaſe: Wee haue thought it neceſſary to redouble our Princely Direction, and ſtrait Charge in that behalfe; wiſhing all men to reſt aſſured, that howſoeuer Our owne nature hath bin alwayes prone vnto mildneſſe and clemencie; yet We are, and ſhall be ſenſible of ſuch preſumption, ſo highly and directly affronting Vs in our Royall commandement.</p>
            <p>And therefore Wee doe by theſe Preſents eftſoones charge and command all maner of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, of what eſtate or degree ſoeuer, That from hencefoorth they preſume not to offend a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Our ſaid former Proclamation, either by licentious and bold Speaking or Writing, or by applauding, entertaining, couering, or concealing ſuch vnfitting Diſcourſe, vpon paine of Our indignation and diſpleaſure, and whatſoeuer other puniſhment ſhall bee meete to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flict vpon ſuch Delinquents.</p>
            <p>And Wee doe further charge and command, not onely Our Officers and Miniſters, but all other our louing Subiects, as they tender Our pleaſure, and will anſwere the contrary, that they vſe all diligence to diſcouer and bring to Iuſtice, all ſuch as ſhall offend in either kind; letting all men know, that Wee will extend the like ſeueritie towards the remiſneſſe of ſuch, who ſhall conceale, as againſt the boldneſſe of audatious Pennes and Tongues, ſo vnreſpec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue of duetie to Gouernment.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Giuen at Our Court at Aſhbie, <date>the ſixe and twentieth day of Iuly, in the nineteenth yeere of Our Reigne of Great Britaine, France and Ireland.</date>
               </dateline>
               <lb/>
God ſaue the King.</closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> Imprinted at London by BONHAM NORTON, and IOHN BILL, Printers to the Kings moſt Excellent Maieſtie. M.DC.XXI.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
